you
everyone
bit
I can help anyone any doubts question to yesterday's session because what was the
question do click the button then it is destroyed but two new button will be
created at its place the next two what it should also behave like the above
button so what is the behavior of the above button the behavior of the above
button yes so what is the behavior of the other button the behavior of the
above button is that on click of the button that button will be destroyed but
two new buttons will be created on its place so what we had done we
implemented it that way right so how did we do that we have a button initially
so we put an event listener on its parent it is double hold down and the
event listener was click so we are listening to click event
is it fine now
great okay so there is a click event that we are listening to on click event
we are doing these many things so basically whatever the question is
asking me to do I'm doing it here so let's go to the question step by step on
click of the button that button will be destroyed we are destroying that button
at the end right it says get two new button will be created so how did we
create button if you remember we created by using something called document dot
create element document is again an object which is provided to us via an
environment which is browser environment so in here we have the
button right I said I simply said why I want to create a button I want to create
an equivalent of this button so what are certain properties of this button the
inner text is saying double so we had wrote this first we created the button
online about 23 then we put the inner text to double exactly like this one
then we also see key by classes also there and it is also said to double so
we simply set my set a new attribute what what attribute I want to set class
and this will be double likewise I created a second button so in this part
I am simply creating two buttons right here it says key but two new buttons
will be created so I was able to create two new buttons now these two buttons
have to be appended somewhere but if these two are created in memory but how
do I bring it out to my Dom so I already have access to my parent double
holder so I said keep a TK whatever button was created simply appended so
this first button got appended to double holder and second button got appended to
double holder then I wanted to destroy the button which was clicked so if you
remember we learned about target and current target in last class target
tells us about the place where the event originated so on click of certain
button only this event must have been originating so from that event or
target I am simply calling remove and that's all I was able to solve for this
problem on click of this button one button will be destroyed and two new
buttons will be added and it will keep on going take a man is it clear
I am audible right
one doubt yes what's it out
you should have written down your doubt at the start only
are you okay we'll take it in doubt session perfect cool so ticket so with
that they can close this close this it is history now now we'll start with
class 13 which is dynamic term and today we will be learning about web APIs
and we will also be integrating our first web API right so first things
first before today's class so today we will be building our first product right
so while building any product I want you to keep certain things in mind right so
first thing is always have first principle thinking what do I mean by
first principle thinking you must have your concepts clear like one such
concept we learned in last class key everything in JavaScript is an object
right so this is a fact it will never change if you have this in mind you sort
of have your first principle thinking clear right so whatever are these
fundamentals of any language you should adhere by it you should say I know for a
factory this won't change so stand by it second while building any project it is
intuition right what do I mean by intuition key while building you should
always have empathy for the end user the person who is going to use your
product right so in that way only you would be able to think about each cases
a chair if I were my end users place I would do this and this might break think
like a hacker key how can I possibly break this once you are able to know key
this is a loophole in your project then go and fix have a fix for it so you
should have a strong intuition he what you are out to build and have empathy
for the end user only then you will be able to think like a product manager or
someone basically be a holistic product person is what I'm trying to say right
thirdly is pretty straightforward without this you cannot build any
project that is
foundation thinking it's simply means you should have your basics clear right
basics as in your HTML CSS JavaScript OSI layers DSA all of these things should
be clear at least the basis I'm not asking you to be able to solve lead code
hard what I'm asking you is you should be able to understand data structure if
you were to break it down data structure how do you structure your data what are
the types of data types which is why if you have your foundational thinking
clear actually big tech companies this is what they focus on the most
especially when they are hiring in bunch foundational thinking which is why you
they are focusing too much on DSA they are focusing too much on JavaScript why
because these are the foundational skills right so if you have these three
things sorted then you should be able to build a project right obviously it is an
iterative process you won't get it right the first time but you will be able to
that is something that I can promise right with that do you want to see the
project that we will be building today we will be building a project using the
knowledge that we have accumulated in the last couple of lectures but do you
want to see the project first or should we start coding Abhinav, Vaima, Dharon,
Ashwini, Krishna, Muniswara, Pradeep, Sambit, Geeta, Raja, do you want to build?
yes project first so let's see the project that we will be building today
so this is the project that we will be building today it is like a wither
application so basically we'll be using some third-party APIs that don't worry
if any of this does not make sense to you we'll be talking about each of each
of these things in detail right so basic HTML and CSS part then something we must
be doing with JavaScript that we are able to get this data like I can change
here and say Mumbai search see I'm getting the data it is getting updated on
click of this if I were to show you the network tab also when I search for tell
me the city that you are from I'll search for the weather there so which
city are you from
Bangalore okay let's search for Bangalore and you will see an API call went and we
got Bangalore so that it is partly cloudy today and the temperature is 25
right we can check for Hyderabad as well yes another API call went so it is 23
then it is partly cloudy there also so Hyderabad is a bit cooler than
Bangalore right so what exactly is this API call right how do you how do we send
this how do we get our self authenticated how do I build this how what
exactly is happening when I click on search we will be discussing all of
these things in today's lecture so are you excited I know I am greater so with
that let us get started so first things first what would happen if I search for
weather today so Google will show me this form of snippet
so Google will show me this form of snippet here right as you could see it
is showing this graph and everything and not sure how is it getting all this
from but when I search for weather today it gives me this much information but
how do I get this information myself right where can I go to get this
information myself and by the way this is something that we will be building
today right so there's this website here called let's say AccuWeather right so
AccuWeather is one such website where you can go and get this data from right
and what exactly is happening here how exactly is it key I am clicking
something here basically opening a URL and I'm getting the data like this how
exactly is this happening so let's go through the network tab once and try and
figure out what exactly is happening here
so let me click on this again and enter you could see a lot of calls went but
where exactly are these call going you must have learned this in the very first
class key how do we get the HTML from right we are getting the HTML I need to
apply filter do you get that thing okay here you probably don't take so here
basically some API call when this particular API call went and in response
to this particular API I get this response does this look familiar to you
yes does this look familiar we have script tag we have for meta tag we have
head tag which language is it correct so basically what is happening key
whenever we search for any website basically a call goes to this particular
place so it just knows key I want to go to this place and you must have learned
about DNS and all of those things eventually you reach a computer
somewhere which we are calling server and that server returns this HTML and
this HTML is returned and then your browser comes in and then your browser
will convert this particular HTML into this website that you are seeing here
right so what is happening there so what is happening there suppose we have for
here website website or here you could say the computer for AccuWeather
AccuWeather and here you have your browser right here is your client which
we also called browser right so and request will basically go from client to
AccuWeather and AccuWeather returns a response and this response is nothing
but an HTML file and once it reaches here then you probably need some sort
of parser to make sense of it right so what are the steps to load a website you
type URL in your browser you go to network tab and then you open a web page
and you get HTML file right and this file is given to your browser which is
also a parser and this browser converts it into the beautiful UI that you see
right are you able to follow till here obviously you must have learned a lot of
things in detail but this is a short story like how you go to a web page you
make an API call basically go to a particular site an HTML file is returned
your browser makes sense out of that HTML file and renders the UI that you
want to play around with correct so far so good now let us talk about parser so
what exactly is this parser that we are talking about what is this parser so
parser you could say is a simple program that reads a particular format of data
and converts that into something else right so some of the examples would be
browser what does it do it is HTML parser it brings out the UI so can you
think of any other parser that takes in a file and it gives you something in
return any other thing think about you have VLC right it takes mp4 format files
and convert it into a video right you have for image viewer it takes in dot jpg
file and converts it into what anyone correct it converts it into an image
right so basically you can keep on going at keyway what does a parser do is what
the parser does is it clear to everyone it is a simple program that reads a
particular format of data data and converts that into something else and
that is exactly what we saw here we were receiving this HTML file this is
hypertext markup language and my browser made sense out of it here I am calling
multiple things I am saying I need this I need this I need this so it is calling
all of those things simultaneously and once it does it basically once it get
all the resources needed for this file it loads the file here right so all good
all good till here everyone is able to follow yes Arun, Ashish, Chandni, Kishore, Krishna,
Munishwara, Digneshwar, Teja, Vishalanya, Sampet correct great great great now
there is something else there is more to it it is not always straightforward as
it is not always straightforward as you will get HTML file so you need more
kinds of data to play around with right so let's go to this website called
weather API right let's go to this website this website I can go to let's say
API Explorer right and here it says key I need to mention the protocol let's say
it's HTTP format I want JSON so and so and so basically when I click show
response I get some kind of response here this is not a correct response that
I was expecting but we get some sort of but we have some sort of response here
so if I were to go here close this and click here you see again I'm making a
thing and I'm getting a response here also we're getting HTML file but we're
getting a response so there can be more than one types of response we need to
add the API key here let me add one in fact let me go to where there are here
you will see when I search for Hyderabad I search for this thing this looks more
or less like the URL that we entered here correct but here we were getting
HTML but here we are not getting HTML instead we are getting some different
kind of data so it is also possible to you hit a endpoint you hit a URL and you
not get HTML now my browser is not able to make sense out of this right so let
me copy this and paste it here I've installed a in this particular browser
it has this thing by default but this is the format that all of you would get
the data in let me paste the link here try opening this link in your browser
try opening it in a new tab you would find something like this right are you
finding something like this yes so this means keep this endpoint gives you data
right this endpoint is live it gives you data but it is not that kind of data
that will be rendered into a webpage so would it be fair to say key I can decide
on what URL I want to send what data back based on that I can do things sort
of right correct so let's show the same thing here so now we have a different
so once again I have another computer this is API dot weather dot com why did
I write API dot weather dot com because if you go here and see here this is what
it is starting with API dot weather dot weather API dot com right and which is
nothing but a web API and this is what we will be playing around today right
and once again we have our client and which client are we using anyone which
client are we using to make a request correct correct correct we are using a
client which is browser and we also call it our web so this client is again
making a request but this time instead of getting a response HTML we are getting
response data which is in a different kind of format right so there is
something really interesting that I just mentioned there is something really
interesting that I mentioned key how am I supposed to how the data is
represented right so there are different formats of representing the data and the
format that we are representing our data in here is a different format I know for
a fact it is not HTML because I know HTML when I see one right so which means key
so which means key we can talk about different formats of data format is the
keyword by the way so let's talk about format for a bit right so let me quickly
mention data representation format so the idea is he I am slowly taking you
towards the project by introducing you to some of the building blocks and then
will accumulate all of the knowledge that we have gathered in last two classes
and whatever we are talking about now and will be building that thing right
then so what are some of the formats that you are aware of one such format
that you may have seen is you open anything so it opens a spreadsheet this
is also sort of a data only right I can mention name age and this thing let's
say name age and city so name is Sashil it is 26 city is Bangalore here name is
let's say age is 28 city is Delhi name is Prakhar age is 29 city is Pune so this is
also I am formatting the data right this is a CSV format right but this would be
exported to Excel a sex right but yes it is one kind of format another kind of
format there could be something called how many I don't know how many of you
have heard of this but earlier back in PHP days there was the data was
transferred in XML format so it was written like this name sorry name
age city
right so this is one such format any other format are you aware of there is
one more kind of format that I'm aware of this is user.json right so we'll talk
about JSON in a bit but yes it is also one such kind of format so it is going
to be like and like this here I'll say name it is like a key value pair
here I could again mention name is Sashwar age is 26 and city is Bangalore
right so basically in such a short span I told you about different kinds of
format so can you help me remind what all other formats that I mentioned so
one was one was definitely CSV right so there is a spreadsheet right you could
have CSVXLXL format and it would be read by these things excel google sheets
likewise we have format for XML which could be read by XML parser then we
would probably have format for JSON can anyone tell me the full form for JSON
this is read by JSON parser by the way
anyone can tell me the full form of JSON JSON actually stands for Java script
object notation so JavaScript already had a has a support for JSON right so
one important thing that I wanted to point out just by having a look at it
one would normally say key it is an object it is a JavaScript object not
JavaScript object notation it is a JavaScript object and this is where
they are wrong right so JSON cannot be an object JSON is always in a string
format the data is only JSON when it is in a string format when it is converted
to a JavaScript variable it becomes a JavaScript object right so those two are
very different right but whenever used in this thing JavaScript we have to make
it into a JavaScript object right now enough talk let's start coding now and
now let's make some API calls right looks like CSS attribute not exactly CSS
attribute but yeah I get your point here so there is this website here I'll close
this close open you Jason type
sorry it is Jason placeholder free fake test API rest API right so let's go in
here so Jason placeholder free fake API so remember we are we were talking about
earlier there are two things firstly there are web APIs and then there are
normal websites which gives you HTML so where can I get this particular data
from so one such example to play around with is Jason placeholder it gives you
free fake API for testing and prototyping right so if I were to scroll down you
would say key some link is mentioned here so let me copy this go here and
paste and enter you see I'm getting the data right so you guys can also paste it
and you would also get some sort of data here right so and if I were to remove
this one you see I'll get a whole lot of data right so normally when people are
getting started this is they are one of their favorite websites in fronting why
because they can go here and get some more data right so now let us quickly
write some code to make use of this thing right so we'll be creating a file
here let's do it in index or HTML right so before we proceed is the this
editor visible to everyone is the text big enough or do you want me to make it
a little more big big enough right cool cool great let me save this right now
it says it is running on 5000 so I'll close this and run it okay and I open
this here now I don't think we need this this not definitely right now we will be
coming back here but let's close this one now I close this for now so right
now we have nothing here right let me quickly making API call let me open the
network tab go to now how do we make API calls from web application how do we
make API calls from web application so there is a method which is given to us
let me open the script so there is a method which is given to us using which
we can make an API call whenever we want right so the end point that we will be
using let me get that JSON placeholder
this right let me paste it so this is the end point that we will be making an API
call with let me open the script tag now and let's write a function foo and
inside of this function I'll be making an API call oh so something there is
something called fetch right can anyone tell me give where will I find fetch we
learned it in the last class where can I find fetch how am I directly able to
write fetch here anyone where exactly do you think fetch would be present it's a
method which is correct but on which object this method is present no HTTP is
the scheme that is a different thing altogether we are not we haven't clicked
anything so event we won't be receiving so I'll tell you so remember I told you
key all such things are present on root level on an object called window so as
you could see I can do window document and this is the entire document
likewise I can enter window you see window has these many things you may
have used alert right so alert is also one such method which is available in
window let me make it so alert is again one such method you have a clear
interval clear time or two probably have not used it yet but they are pretty
useful right likewise here you will find fetch and what does fetch do fetch MDN
fetch provides an interface for fetching resources right so wherever we will be
fetching resources we are I'm basically saying I will be going to this place and
I'll fetch the resource and we had already seen key from this I'll be getting a
JSON in return right so JSON is the resource that I am fetching using the
fetch API right is everyone able to follow just a quick yes no yes T so now
I know for a fact key I have to use fetch cool so let's simply make use of
it and in an ideal world it would work right so I already have the link with me
let me copy this paste it here and let me store the response here and I can do
console dot log response right so I need to execute the function take I just
executed the function as well now they good right we should be able to get the
data now let's go and see where our data is I'll go to document and here it is
saying hmm I'm not seeing my data instead I'm seeing here something called
promise which is pending right so promise is a fairly advanced topic so we
won't get into it right now right in future you have in total of three
classes around this so let me quickly tell you in brief key why this is
happening and what's the way around it okay so let me mention key say there is
this guy named for sure and I am taking the class in this and this is the
timeline of the class right this is the start this is the end right and I am
moving in this direction slowly slowly but what if someone asks a doubt here I
will address the doubt and let's say it took me around two minutes so which
means keep post this when the doubt is clear I'll again start going going going
from where I left off I left off here so I'll start from there and I'll keep on
going until someone else's interjects again being the guy I am again I address
the doubt and it will again take me some time so would you say key this is the
best way to conduct a class yes or no key every time I am waiting for some
time before moving forward right so it is not exactly the best way to conduct
the class and ultimately I reached here so what could be the other way that we
could probably have conducted this so this was again the start this is again
the end and this time I am by conducting the class I keep on going and when
they have a doubt I will postpone this doubt to end right so let's say and I
have a bucket prepared so I have mentioned their doubt here and I can
continue from there itself then again someone has a doubt again I'll take this
out and put it at the end right and this way I am able to conduct the class in a
more fluent manner right there are two thumbs down uncle and Tejan are saying
this is not the way to conduct a class but take it so out of these two ways
this the first way of conducting the class is you could say I am doing
things in a
well up in a synchronous manner right and in the second way I'm doing things
in a asynchronous manner right so yeah it's fine to take it so the first thing
I we are doing it in synchronous manner and the second we are doing in a
synchronous manner so in synchronous manner I am supposed to stop to get the
data to get the data and then moving forward right and in asynchronous manner
I'll keep on moving forward so JavaScript whenever someone asked you
is JavaScript synchronous or asynchronous JavaScript is synchronous
and if you think about it getting the data from somewhere why does it need
internet because your request actually goes to that server right your request
actually goes from your computer point A to point B and this round trip is
supposed to take some time which is why if you see here I'll go to network
tab here it says mentions a time as well right this took three seconds three
milliseconds if I go here and I refresh go to the top it takes 190 milliseconds
so this one to 90 milliseconds is the time it took to cover this round trip
now some would say key it is fast but in computer terms every millisecond every
nanosecond counts so this means keep this is basically taking sometimes a
JavaScript has two things that they could do it could either wait or it
could keep on moving forward so the reason that you are getting pending for
this one here is because it moved forward even though it is synchronous
because of promises and callback and asynchronous behavior it was able to
move forward but don't worry about it you'll worry about you'll learn about it
in future class but this is just to give you an idea keep this is how
JavaScript works so basically it went it moved forward it moves forward saying
I promise I promise keep when I get the data I will let you know right so which
is why you are getting a promise here interesting right the names also there
put it in such a way can you starts making sense so now we'll go back here
and now how can I figure it out till so here I can add a simple thing called a
sick at the start by writing a sink here I'm mentioning kibbit this function will
perform asynchronously right and I am to write a weight here so which means key
when I'm making this API call I will JavaScript will actually wait on this
line he until and unless I get a response I won't move forward right so
now I save this and I'll go back here now this time you can see I got
something I got something right but this is again not the kind of response that I
was expecting correct why because this again needs a asynchronous behavior I
cannot use it so let me say first Jason is equal to a weight response dot Jason
and I can paste this here and now I can go and now you see I'm getting the data
here interesting right now I may be able to get the data so this again
response dot Jason was an asynchronous start so which is why it was again
breaking I put a weight here and by the way I can only put a weight inside of
asynchronous functions so I cannot just put a weight here and expect it to work
if I were to remove this you'll see it start giving an error key await
expressions are only allowed within async functions and that top level of
modules right so I need to write async here and not as soon but async here and
save this so this way I am getting the response what we want now I can use this
response and put it in dong you know how to do that you can target the H1
element and simply in inner text paste this thing and it would work right but
how we are making the API call and these two line basically is it clear to
everyone why a response dot Jason here so response is not in the exact structure
that we could utilize it so which is why it needs to be converted into Jason
remember I mentioned that Jason is the formatted JavaScript understands so this
is a actually a method to convert it into that but this function is
asynchronous so which means we have to put a weight here otherwise as you saw
we would be getting an error let's try to answer your query cool great yeah so
with that I think we are all set now we can get started with the project but
before we get start with a project we have one tiny bit one tiny thing to do
and what is that as you could see here also wherever I am making the where will
I get this URL from right so let us figure out a way to get this URL first
before we get started right let me close Jason placeholder now that part is done
I'll go to whether API in here so here it gives you free weather API right I can
go to pricing and you could see for zero dollar per month we get these many
things in a month I can make 1 million calls which is 10 lakh calls and so many
things it is providing right if I were to pay seven dollar per month then I'll
have these many things but for today's session we will be relying on the free
version and you can keep on going up and up and up and you can expect some sort
of API is here right we want this one so let's get started with that I will I've
already created an account here is it real time or dummy placeholder this is
the weather API is not dummy the one the plug Jason placeholder that we were
using that was to me this is real time right so you can sign up here I had
already created an account so I am going to login but once you sign up and I will
see more or less the same thing I just logged in here and it says I have these
many things with me my free trial apparently ends on 15th of 4th so before
that we need to finish this lecture I don't need any of these things let's go
to something called so this is the part what exactly is this API key that you
are seeing this is interesting so when you log in or when you sign up you will
land on this dashboard you will get a unique API key now think of it this way
key if hitting an API is as simple as like this API I can copy and paste it
if it is as simple as this won't anyone will be able to do that yes or no it is
as simple as copy and paste every time someone copy and paste a call goes to
these guys whether API and they send this data back and how much time is it
taking to bring this data can anyone tell me so how much time is it taking to
get me this data current.json it says 278 no correct it is 211 millisecond so
think of it this way I can possibly spread this URL everywhere and everyone
use it how can these guys tell key whether Shashwat is consuming this API
or Ankit is consuming this API Upendra, Ashi, Shambhu Rajan who is consuming this API
and this is the authentication so if I were to if you could see here these are
called query params so dissect URL and I can show here only no in here just a
second I can go to payload so as you could see these are the three query
params that I'm sending while making this particular API call in header right
one is the key second is the query second and third is the AQI so whatever
query we are writing like in this particular case it was Hyderabad so we
are sending I want data for this I don't want AQI and this is the key so this key
is nothing but the key which is mentioned here I'm using someone else's
apparently so which is why the key seems different but if I were to let's
say copy this and I want to paste this is some 802 right I'll paste my I'll
paste I'll copy and paste my key here and enter it will work but suppose if I
were to make changes to this to and make it zero right now it is saying the API
key has been disabled right and if I don't send this key at all right I'll
get API key invalid or not provided right so because why did they send this
because there was no way for these guy to verify K by who is trying to consume
my API until and unless someone they are able to identify who is this person
they won't be able to make changes in their dashboard he why you have already
used hundred API calls you have already used two thousand API calls so if you
want to create your own simply sign up with weather API right weather API dot
com and you will land on this dashboard you will get your own personal key which
you could use correct now let's go to document and now one last thing these
are all query params right so key is an important query param it helps weather
API to identify who is trying to consume query is my query give I I want to
search for Hyderabad suppose if I want to search for something random something
right and search in this case I'm getting an error put a valid location will be
building this also by the way and you will see I'm sending the query as this
IQ I still has no and in preview I'm getting this response this again is in
JSON format right so now with that be clear now we can get started
I do this so now let's get started building the project right so all that
story for this part I'll close the snippets part now we'll get started
rebuilding index.html script.js and style.js right I can close this this
now before we proceed I just want to hear it from everyone he is everyone
able to follow till now yes Abhinav, Ankit, Abhimanyu, Ahmed, Arun, Ashish, Ashwini,
Chandni, Dhanraj, Hemant, Kishore, Krishna, Munishwara, Pradeep, Prajakta, Pramod, Raja, Rita, Sahil,
Sandhya, Sheik, Sharanya, Tejal, Upendra, Vigneswar, Vinay, Priyanko, Rohit, Shambhu, Raje
everyone able to follow okay that's fine that's more than fine Ankit but I hope
you you get the crux of it right great great great so with that now I can go
here and here there is something called API Explorer I can go here and your API
key let me get my API need to get it from manually now they built sort of a UI
for me remember we were getting an error here that was the reason I'll paste my
API key here I'm searching for London show response and this time I'm getting
200 success as you could see this is the end point URL that they are hitting and
this is the response that they are giving right so all is sorted now now
all I have to do is build a UI and consume this API so let's get started I
can probably close this and do I need this yes I will be needing this so
instead of snippet I can simply do this enter and in here and mention hello see
we're getting hello so we're in the right file now now all we have to do is
implement a project so let's get started
Tiga so this is the way that at least I proceed so first things first we need
the HTML then we need to apply the CSS and then we'll get to the main part
which is JavaScript right so HTML and CSS should not be a big hurdle for you
guys at this point considering you have already finished the first module so I
will be skipping directly to the JS part of things right so anyway let's get
started and I tell you think about the structure of this right you basically see
two diffs here right there is a container in that container in that
container you have this thing a weather app in this particular weather app you
could see you have this this is just a second so this is the container and this
is the now so there are two sections that you want to play around with
correct and these two sections exist inside of your body and once you start
going in you can see you have a weather here and here you have your temperature
time location weather and you can keep on further going in and you will find
he how they are structured right pretty simple HTML at this point just a div
which has another div which will be which has another div couple of and you
can keep on going and keep on building your HTML so with that being said let
us go to let me bring out the HTML here so this is a structure that we are to
follow right so just a second so same structure in body in body I have two
sections one is container one is now if I were to expand now you would find I
have a text input for me and I have a button and that is exactly what you see
here I have an input screen I have a button now I can close this now I can go
to container control to weather did inside I had three things so container
is basically the whole thing the whole blackish thing that you are seeing that
is the container inside of this container we had made a weather which is
basically a wrapper around this section right and in this section we have three
things if you see we have one div here we have one so we have one div here we
have one div here and we have one dip here and if you think about it all of
these tips are sort of in a row so which means keep huh you can copy paste it
from inspect but a lot of other things would also come which you might find
consuming so I would suggest you do not anyway I'll be pushing the code so you
can just copy paste it from there right TGA and in here this will be centered
align this is all three are center align but here you have two divs now so one
div at the top one div at the bottom here you also have one div at the top
one div at the bottom and that is exactly you will see here this thing is
single-handed in time location you have a P you have a span in weather condition
you must be having image and you have the condition right so in here we are
getting the styles from style and we are getting the scripts from script or just
which by the way both are empty right now right so let me save this and see
what the HTML looks like right now so this is what your HTML looks like right
now so quick question does it look like this yes or no
are both of these apps similar no right take it now this again a little bit
amazes me every time see how much change the look and feel CSS could bring
although that's its entire job but still this is play such a critical role
because it just changes the entire trajectory of the app it makes it so
well up at least aesthetic to look at if if done correctly that goes without
saying let me add the CSS simple things simple classes simple all of these
things you must have heard about flexbox and all here we are using grid and you
may have read about grid also in some of the previous classes some places we had
used flex some places we had to use grid you can go through this after class once
I push the code right now let's go back here now do they look alike yes great
great great take it so now we will be starting with the main part actually
applying the knowledge that we have accumulated in last couple of classes so
for that let us take a quick break and when we are back for the break then
this get started with the script or JS part and we will right now as you could
see this is not functional at all if I do anything nothing is happening I'm
trying to click nothing is happening nothing is happening no API calls are
going on so I would close this do this nothing is happening right so now we
will be applying JavaScript and using the newly found API this API to get the
data here right so we'll be doing this after the break right now it is what
time it is it is 10 o 7 let's connect at 10 13 right 10 minutes my god he got
10 minutes about good number there so it's 10 minutes party party time
okay so at 10 what time now at 10 17 we'll connect right so let me start
a timer
nine minutes if not the whole year now start
take care go for a break meanwhile if any one of you has any doubt regarding
anything we can discuss and you and CSS yes we are importing the forms from
Google API's we must be using it also the Roboto font we have put it in font
family simple thing only yeah it's nothing much here container better
whether anyone else has any doubt while others go for water go for a walk
stretch your legs now we'll be starting with a meaty part of the project which
is see writing actual JavaScript making an API call get the data and update our
dog I just want to see the class names class names leto I think this would be
the best place now see the class names wherever we have this
meanwhile anyone else has any doubt
you
join now was stuck in a meeting
so the rich we were mostly talking about the difference in between HTML response
and some Jason response different formats we went on to talk about some
weather APIs that we could use we break down how they are authenticating us how
do they know key whether it's making this API call or making this API call
and lastly we went to this one website called Jason placeholder which gives us
mock APIs dummy APIs dummy data so through that we were able to get the
response and now we just started with a project we are set out to build this
project with that app today you could search for any city and it would provide
you the data for that so we are building this we just finished HTML and CSS part
now after 5 minutes and 24 seconds we will be starting with JavaScript
don't worry sir anyway you have five minutes you were stuck in a meeting so go have some
water in five minutes will begin right meanwhile if anyone else has any doubt
regarding anything that we had covered now in today's class please ask
I'm audible now
so let's get started so most probably you didn't hear the answer also that I was
giving for your question key whether it would do we need to enter correct spellings to
search or it will manage right okay so the answer is no it won't it is not that
will make it is like a free thing so get nine chair so we decide won't but how do
they do it is pretty interesting so you could Google about it it's called fuzzy
search fuzzy search so Google about it it tells you okay how it works right pretty
interesting to get I hope the screen is also shared and I'm audible right just a quick
show of hands great okay so before we begin let me launch the poll so once again I'm
launching the poll let's see if you guys send it at 50 50 this time or not right
so launching the poll now in three two one
okay okay
someone mess it up at the end yes cool so as I said I mentioned this before also none
able to make it 50 50 and considering this is my last class here you also won't be able
to end it at 50 58 great so with that now I feel good and it's a challenge sort of
a thing it's not something that I want to get so let's get started so so far what we
had done we had we have the HTML and CSS in place now all we have to do is figure out
the API call and if you were to refer one of the snippets that we had done we had already
know how to make the API call also right we already know how to make the API call also
so with that knowledge in place let's get started so let's get started with the basics
so let's get started so we are listening to now because in now we have the input present
right so we are ought to listen to the input so we need to target it first right only then
we can listen to the change events so let's do that first correct so I'll go to script.js
and I can listen to const search button document dot query selector we want to search for search
is the search name here the class is present search and it is unique to it so let's do
dot search now that I have searched with me I can attach a event listener add event listener
we are listening to which event click event and we need to provide a call back to this
and in this call back will be getting a event so let me quickly check if we are receiving
the event yes we are receiving the event so we also need to attach event listener to the
because that's where we will be getting the data from I can say document dot query selector dot
search field that's it right and in here I can bulky say search field dot let's go for search
field and let's see what do we get right so let's go here and I'll clear this go to console
and I'll say here let's say and press enter see I'm able to get the event and on this
I don't have the value so I can probably get the value from this so let me search for Delhi
and we're able to get the data so remember the API call that we were doing for this API call I
have the key with me correct I have the AQI value with me it is always going to be no and
now for query which is the what city am I searching for I have the Delhi also in place
so whatever the user types when they click search I have that also with me now so which
means key all I have to do now is make an API call with this would you all agree yes
should we go ahead and implement the API call part now so now all we have I can now say
fetch temperature for this so now if I go here and search for Mumbai fresh temperature
for Mumbai so I know so let me have a function here and we can call this function fetch weather
right we will be passing the city name here and considering kid we will be making an API call so
is there anything that I need to put in front of this function any any keyword that you may have
seen character we need to put a sink in front right now that we have a sink in front I can
go in here and say the same thing right considering key fetch weather and here
I can pass search field dot value and what I can say is event dot prevent default so prevent
default whatever is a default behavior it would stop that and it would simply do this right so
let's case let's see if the this was a form it button type submit case the page would have
refreshed so which is why if I were to remove this also it would it would work is it fine now
great yes I'll go a little slow so event or prevent before basically says keep whatever is
the default behavior it will stop that right it won't make it do that well even if I were
to remove it it would still work but this is just for your understanding to put it at a start that's
it right we don't need to get into detail for this in future when in the next class action when
you start building your next project there you will be seeing this in action in detail right so
right now if invoke the cancel attribute value set to true while executing the listener of the
event with passive set to for signals to the operation that caused event to dispatch but
it's a lot written here so let's wait for the next class in next class while you start building
board there you'll be seeing it in action take so now it is working now I can go here I can
search for a location enter fetch temperature for this so it is working so now comes the actual
API call part right so what is the URL const URL is equal to let me get the URL from here
take I'll make it in tick and I'll make this one as city name and I'll take it out and say
const API to gun right and paste it here take now my URL is ready what whatever is the query
I have a URL for that right now all I have to do is follow whatever we had done here so let me
copy paste it go back to script and here I can do this but instead of this one I'll say URL right
so now when I'll do console dot log parsed JSON or I'm missing
you can work with normal quotes also prefer it this so this way I can add things directly
inside I don't need plus posting so which is why it's the voice pack just a second
it's the just a second let me share my screen again take it is the voice back
I've been on our sheesh Muneeswara some bit upendra great in case it gets
let me know how I've reduced the screen quality just so my voice is better okay
but I'm assuming key you would still be able to read it through right zoom a little okay let
me make it a little bit now it should be whispered great Tia so what I had done here is that I have
the I'm using backticks they could have done it directly so what I have done here instead
of using the plus thing you could use that that is perfectly fine I prefer backticks
because I can directly put things in my string only I don't need to do plus plus and all of
those things so I find it this way a little clean so that's the only reason that I have gone with
this way but either way is fine and these two lines is something that I had copied from this
part that this part that we had seen earlier right so with that let's save this now tell me
if it would work if I were
sir
we got the response so congratulations we have the response in place
is the net back
now I'm checking my internet connection again I'm checking my internet connection
so
I will go slow, anyway we are almost there, hardly 15 minutes you need to manage and we
are good.
Hardly 15 minutes of content is left then we are good.
So if you guys are okay we can move forward right?
Cool cool cool, okay so we are able to make the API call and what am I doing?
I am preparing my URL, I am getting the search field when the user is clicking on the search
button, sending it to this function fetchweather and from fetchweather I am preparing this
URL with the API token and city name and simply making the API call using fetch which is
present on window object.
I am using await because this is an asynchronous operation, likewise converting the response
into JSON is again an asynchronous process so which is why I had put await here.
So once here I get the response that we are actually looking for right?
So now let us use this response to get the things that we want right?
So before we do let me go here and let's see the kind of response that we had received.
I can expand, you could see in current I am getting, feels like I am getting the actual
temperature that we probably want to put here right?
What else am I getting?
I am getting the wind also in case you want, I am getting the last time it was updated,
I already have the location with me because this is what the user has typed, I can close
go to location, here you could see I have the country, location, longitude, latitude,
what's the local time, we have all of these information and all of this information is
pretty important right?
And I also have the icon also present here that we want to load in here.
So long story short, I have whatever data I want to get here, I have all of those data
present with me.
So all we have to do is take that data and inject it into the DOM and how do we inject
it into the DOM?
Using the methods we had learned in last couple of classes, cool?
Is everyone able to follow till now?
I hope the voice and all is ok?
We will get to that, but you won't get the idea where I am heading with this.
Now I have the data with me, all I have to do is get the relevant data and inject it
in my DOM right?
So I am able to follow right Shambhu, Raje, Vinay, Avinav, Ankit, Pradeep, Dhanraj, great,
great, great, great.
So let's go ahead and get the data first right?
We already have the past, this thing in place.
Let me say current temperature is equal to first Jason dot, current dot, temperature
C. Temperature is centigrade, second.
Let's get current condition, this also in condition we get the text and icon right?
So we probably need both of these things.
So dot condition dot text, copy paste and I can say condition icon, here I can get condition
dot icon.
What else do we need?
So you probably need a location name and local time, I think these should be enough.
So let's see, I close current, I will go to location, location name is location dot name
and time is location dot local time right?
So let's go with this, location name is location dot name and this is location dot local time.
Now let me console this so we can just see if we have everything that we want.
We have current time, we have current condition, we have current icon, we have we have local.
Now if I search for Mumbai, what happened, error, see the data that we are creating.
So if I were to expand this, this is the data that we wanted, condition icon that will
go here, current condition, current temperature, local time and location name.
So basically we have all the data that we need.
Now all we have to do is utilize it right?
One thing we forgot to do, in case it breaks how to handle it.
So to handle all of these, JavaScript gives us a function, these things try catch, almost
every language does.
So let me take all of these things and put it into try and add a catch key, in case any
of this thing breaks, just go to catch and I can start an alert saying, please put a
valid query right?
And I can console the log for the developer in console dot error, I can share the error.
So this way if it breaks, it would go here, I'll see an alert and I'll see the error
as well, right?
So try catch is a mechanism to handle now if this block, within this block, if anything
breaks, anything, no matter what, my application won't be, you know, gone, right, my application
won't crash.
I'll receive an error here so that I can handle it.
So it is a very neat way of handling errors, right?
Even in production, great application, everyone uses it.
So try catch is a very, very good tool for you to know about, right?
Great.
Now we have this information, all we have to do is update the DOM.
So shall we go ahead and update the DOM now?
We already have these things in place in HTML, we have all the classes in place.
So let me open it in the site, close it and now, and now I'm going to get the class names
from here.
I'll get the class names from here and I will update it.
So let's first of all get the selectors in place so that we should be able to get it,
right, say const temperature field, temperature field, document dot query selector.
I see the classes there of 10, so I can do it like this.
Likewise, I can add city field classes there as dot time underscored location inside of
it, p tag, right?
And this is date file, you could say, and for the remaining two fields, one is your
dot weather, sorry, one is your icon field, the icon field, icon field in weather condition,
the image tag, right?
So I can say dot weather condition img and lastly, we have another field condition is
left, right?
So I can say weather field and here I can say weather underscore condition span, okay?
I think we have covered all the fields from here, right?
Or am I missing?
Is the screen still blurry?
Let's wait it out there.
Let me know once it's fine.
Anyway, here we are simply targeting the elements.
From CSS part, you haven't get what, what was it in CSS that you haven't get exactly
That is fine, but whatever we are talking about, that is clear to you, right?
Well, the JavaScript part is not clear.
That is clear, right?
So I'm not sure what is not clear.
I get it.
The screen is blurry, but the concept at least the idea that I'm trying to convey that is
clear to you guys, right?
Because if that is clear, you can always revisit a repository.
I'll be pushing this code so you can get the code from there.
If the concept is clear, you still would be able to understand and in case you still have
doubt, obviously I am there on the group to answer all your queries, right?
So let me know if the screen is a little better, then we'll move forward.
We just have one last leg to complete and then we are all good.
Better now?
Great, great, great.
Cool, yeah.
Let me know in case it gets blurred.
We'll again wait it out.
No worries.
We have, we still have ample of time.
So what I had done here, I was able to make the API call and from that API, I am able
to extract the data.
As you saw, I'm also able to log it here, right?
So now the idea is I should be able to update my HTML with this data.
So for that to go for that to happen, we had to select using the query selector, right?
Using the query selector, I had attached able to target each of these elements.
Now, all I have to do is literally just do inner text, inner text, inner text and update
the values that you see here.
There.
Cool.
So let us go ahead and do that, right?
So just a second.
Let me write another function here.
Update DOM here.
I'll be getting all of these things.
This part I can close, right?
The HTML part, which is fine.
Even if it takes time, it is fine.
I'll wait it out.
Yes.
So whatever things were here, I had written it down here.
Now, all I have to do is simply update it, right?
So let's do that.
Now, this part is fine.
Okay?
So I will say...
ta ta ta ...
Good.
So let me bring these elements at the bottom so that I can comment it so that I don't have
to scroll up every time right now I can focus here t so first things first temperature field dot
inner text is equal to current temperature right then we have city field dot inner text
icon field icon field is nothing but an image so I can I can choose to say dot set attribute
because I want to update the SRC there with the value that we are receiving which is condition
icon right and lastly we have weather field dot inner text is equal to
correct condition right so let's go here and now I'll search for Mumbai and press search
oh my bad I forgot to call this function so with this here I just need to do this and
say now when I go Mumbai research it is getting updated right was everyone able to follow yes
how's the screen situation right now better than before or still still worse now good right so
everyone is able to follow right now I can play around with it I can add for it is updating I
can add it is updating it is night there apparently right so all of this is well yes we can use
actuals also but I wanted to use vanilla JavaScript so without using any other library I wanted to
do this so which is why I've done it this way right but yes you can use actuals also that is
perfectly fine T so how about I add a little check here key if let me say const city name
how they are getting the city name I'm sorry I can say const city name is equal to this thing
and I can put a check here if city name city name is there go ahead basically city name is
equal to empty string empty string in that case let's say if city name is there basically let's
go with that that is much easier to comprehend so if city name is there only then it would make
API call otherwise it won't let's test it out by actuals is better than actuals can you please
other by then fetch so actuals internally does nothing it is fetch only so it is like a wrapper
right so there's a lot of things that actuals take care of you which otherwise you have to do
it manually so nothing else so it is the same as key same question is asking key why is sir
automatic car better than manual car you still have to drive but automatic car takes care of
certain things for you that's it actuals is a library to make fetch API calls it's a wrapper
muniswara it's just a fancy way of making API calls that's it can we add degree celsius
I don't see why not so there is something called superscript if I'm not wrong oh there is
this current temperature
dollar and here I can add
matter
let's see if it looks good
uncut says to blood
uncut is it still blurred for you the whether the screen is blurred or not that is not important
are you able to understand what we are trying to learn that is important you're able to write
okay now tell me the part if it was not blurred you want to see I'll go there and I'll wait for
screen to be better okay so by the way we had successfully finished the project and we have
successfully able to build right now in case you have any doubts uncut up enough I know the screen
was blurred so in case you have any doubts explain code of script or js array we've been doing that
only in a sensor side but okay so we have the html in place so we have to attach event listeners
so first thing that we did was we attached the event listeners to each of the available fields
there on index.html then one such field was search button I'd attach an event listener there what
event are we listening to is the voice still breaking
the data part we are talking about some that we'll get to it I'm okay it's good for me good for me
good for me now I'm getting mixed with you some of you are saying it's good some of you are saying
it's not some mostly Abhinav and uncut are saying it's not good do you know what is
not good do you know what is Abhinav is it fine for you now shall I go ahead
cool so on search button we had attached a event listener what event are we listening to we are
listening to click event and we attached a callback so if someone were to press the click by the time
the city name was empty nothing would happen because this condition would be false
right but in our case if city name is there we are actually making an API call here we are passing
the city name to we are passing the city name to fetch weather function what does the fetch
weather function do it will make an API call using fetch we are making the url they're getting the
token which is sort of fixed only then we have the city name we have the aq i said to know city
name is something that we are getting from the input field if you remember and we are making
the API call and converting it into the json format which your javascript understands
once it does we are taking out necessary feeds from this parse json that I need to populate my
ui my ui right so like I need the Celsius thing I need a location name I need a local time I need
a condition right so I take out all of these things from the response that I get from this url
right once I do I am passing the response in update.dom update.dom is again a function that
I have defined where I am whatever event targets the elements that I had selected here
I'm simply doing inner text in each one of them except one where it is an image so I am setting
the src to the condition that's it I'm setting the inner text to the value that we are getting
a response that we had got in here and that's it once it does that it starts reflecting there
and one other thing that I had done I dropped the entire code so this is the only place where
anything could possibly go wrong if it does it is still in try catch so my application won't crash
instead it would go to catch block and in catch block I would catch the error and I will be
putting it a alert out and that's how the whole application that you are seeing here would work
is it fine now are you guys able to follow so with that great great great great yeah so
so that's it folks
uh I've stopped sharing my screen uh it's okay I've started a doubt solving session now
if any one of you has any doubt regarding anything that we had discussed today
now is the time so any one of you if have any doubt
any doubts anyone and obviously from next class onwards Uttam will be back and he'll be
taking the class forward so I hope the last three classes there weren't much complaints
or you guys from my side right
I hope the last three classes it wasn't much big of an issue
I am what can I do I raised a complaint with geo for this they said they'll be coming over to
check it over I think on Friday or Saturday they'll come thank you thank you
thank you Manish for our thanks meanwhile any doubts anyone
no doubts
all good then
uh one advice from my side would be to keep on practicing the assignment question
because assignment questions at scalar are designed in such a way that if you are able
to complete assignment question obviously you'd be able to clear the mock interviews also right
and if you are able to perform good and mock interviews scalar
would put in extra effort in placing you at the end how the data is extracted
data is extracted through destructuring have you guys covered this yet because
I remember it being one of the topic
so it is simply adjacent right I'm calling it adjacent but it is more or less like an object
so like you pass objects that is exactly how I am parsing it here so I'm simply going down
pass json.current.tempc pass json.current.condition.text so I have the object with me the response object
and I have the response object with me and I'm simply going down in current by
what is their condition condition text so I'm simply going down this part that's it
using the dot notation that's you may have learned
how you do in object data structure just that way nothing special right
Sambit is it out clear
can you share your experience with geocinema how the tasks are given
just to know real time things it is very fast paced and believe it or not whatever you guys
are learning this is what we do on a day-to-day basis because this is these are the foundational
things if you are able to clearly understand these three things html css javascript everything
else is smoke and mirrors right everything else no matter what fancy framework you pick be it
a this thing react view angular svelte no matter what you pick all of that is smoke and mirrors
everything boils down to html css and javascript so just focus on this frameworks will come and go
basics will stay forever so just focus on this and you'll be good and believe it or not
uh that works for me a geo also
or a which framework is trending now a lot of frameworks are trending yeah
i mean i'm not keeping tabs but last i checked svelte and vue js are doing good
so
cool
cool then uh if no other doubts
five for web 10 where js is used i mentioned now just change the environment and it can be used
anywhere you can make at today's time you can make mobile apps with it desktop apps with it
vr apps with it so you can do a lot of things with js in today so js is everywhere so which is why
you can pick the domain also later you just need to have your basics clear right now
uh
cool
cool then yeah uh so that's it from my side and uh hopefully uh maybe in some future classes
when uttam is not there i can again uh join him fill in for him right so thank you all thank you
all for being patient thank you all for showing on a non-class day again i'm really sorry for the
internet connectivity it is not something in my control uh so with that i think i
i'll say adios to you guys and let me just put this option in my screen
cool uh with that i think i'll take your leave now i'll be leaving now there right bye i'll see you
guys around
i'll upload the notes and i'll inform on the group right bye
thank you thank you everyone bye
you